[Claire] Previously...
[Young Ian]
Built yer house for ye.
I'm so overwhelmed.
I'd be lying if I said
I wasn't a wee bit selfish
in putting this together,
seeing as I have your first two
patients.
[Claire] Is it really you?
-Oh, darling.
-[laughter]
[Brianna]
We wanted to come home.
Captain Charles Cunningham.
You fought for the king then.
I laid down my sword for good.
You are all undoubtedly
going to hell.
I think perhaps
that witch is Mrs. Cunningham.
I will remain in America
with Mercy.
We wish to be wed.
Henry, marriages
of this sort are illegal.
Ben is dead.
He was taken prisoner while
out with a raiding party.
A young lady appeared
on my doorstep with her baby,
claiming she was
Benjamin's widow.
[Claire] "Soul of a Rebel"
by Franklin W. Randall.
What does it say?
That war is coming,
and that James Fraser
dies in it.
[indistinct chatter]
[laughs]
Oh, my word.
Ben.
Let me see the letter.
[chuckling]
It becomes you.
Yes, I know.
Where is it you'll be sent?
Boston.
I'm to report
to General Howe's detachment
as soon as we set foot
in America.
Where?
There.
[laughs]
Oh, General Rol n.
I can't believe
you still have him.
Of course I still have him.
You gave him to me when
I first came to this house.
You made me feel
a part of this family.
[soft music plays]
Since he was always
my best fighter,
I want you to take him with you
for good fortune.
As you know, he hasn't
ever lost a battle.
[chuckles]
? ?
I promise I shall keep him
right here with me
for as long as
I wear this uniform.
I know he'll guard me well,
cousin.
? ?
? Sing me a song ?
? Of a lass that is gone ?
? Say, could that lass ?
? Be I? ?
? Merry of soul ?
? She sailed on a day ?
? Over the sea ?
? To Skye ?
? Billow and breeze ?
? Islands and seas ?
? Mountains of rain ?
? And sun ?
? All that was good ?
? All that was fair ?
? All that was me ?
? Is gone ?
? Sing me a song ?
? Of a lass that is gone ?
? Say, could that lass ?
? Be I? ?
? Merry of soul ?
? She sailed on a day ?
? Over ?
? The sea ?
? To Skye ?
[dramatic music plays]
? ?
You mean anytime
I take a drink of water,
I'm swallowing all of that?
Yes, but don't worry.
Most of what you're looking at
is perfectly harmless.
And it'll be dissolved
by your stomach acid.
But there are plenty
of nasty things in water.
Acid?
In my stomach?
But wouldn't that just
eat right through things?
That's how your food
is digested.
But your stomach walls
are very thick,
and they're covered
in mucus, so...
My stomach is full of snot?
[laughs]
You find mucus in most
of the inside of your body.
You have these things
called mucus membranes,
and they secrete mucus
whenever your body
needs help with a little bit
of slipperiness.
Oh, is that what women have
between their legs to make-
Yes.
When you're pregnant,
you need that slipperiness
to help the baby come out.
So all these things are here
all the time,
but we can't see them?
That's right.
I wish Janie was here.
She would have loved this.
[somber music plays]
Whenever she would hear
of a curiosity,
she'd tell me about it.
? ?
Mrs. Abbott, the madame,
didn't like such talk
and forbade it.
She thought Jane was strange
and accused her
of practicing the dark arts.
The men seemed to like
her strangeness,
especially the soldiers.
Come here.
Let me tell you something.
Fanny,
I know you've seen
some terrible things.
I have, too.
So you can say anything to me.
I won't be shocked.
All of the family-
Mr. Fraser,
Mr. and Mrs. MacKenzie-
you can tell them anything
at any time.
But...
some of the people
on the Ridge,
they won't have had the same
experiences as you and I.
And, well,
they might be shocked
if you told them very much
about how you used to live.
They've never met whores.
I think some of the men
must have.
I'm sure you're right.
But we wouldn't want anyone to
make any assumptions about you
or think that they have
the right to do things to you
that they do not.
Does that mean I shouldn't
talk about Jane either?
No, no.
You can talk about your sister
whenever you like.
[soft music plays]
? ?
She wanted to protect you
from that life,
and she tried to keep you safe.
And now...
we will keep you safe, always.
? ?
Go on.
Look at the rest of the slides.
[sighs]
[Jamie] Dougal's son?
William Buccleigh MacKenzie.
We called him Buck.
Aye, he stayed in 1739.
We asked him to come with us,
but I couldn't convince him.
Ah, 'twas good of ye
to forgive him-
a man who'd have ye hanged?
[grunts]
[pants]
[log snapping]
[sniffles]
I'm not sure
I could have done the same.
He's a good man.
Sometimes good men do things,
thinking them right,
only to realize later
that they were mistaken.
Shouldn't we forgive that?
And he's family.
I love him for that alone.
[Jamie sighing]
[grunting]
I was wonderin' if you could
advise me on something.
I'd be happy to.
Yeah.
I've been reading Frank's book.
It says a battle is coming
to the backcountry.
The Patriots will win
because the Overmountain men
call upon each other.
A John Sevier,
a Benjamin Cleveland, and a-
a Isaac Shelby.
Do you ken any of these names
from history?
I mean...
No.
I've never heard of any
of those names before.
But then again,
the Revolutionary War
in North Carolina wasn't
my academic speciality.
Says I'll fight alongside them.
But I dinna ken
any of those men.
Are you sure it's you?
There are a good many men named
James Fraser in Scotland.
And I'm sure there
are plenty here, too.
Aye, but if it is me, then...
...if Frank kent who I was,
didn't have any reason
to love me.
Do you want me to read it?
-Maybe.
-[horse nickers]
Once I'm finished.
Mr. Fraser!
Well met.
[Jamie] Captain Cunningham.
I received word
you wished to see me.
I stopped by your house,
and your wife mentioned
I'd find you here.
Thanks for coming.
You, uh-
you already ken my son-in-law,
Roger MacKenzie.
Yes, we spoke a few days ago.
I'm pleased to see you again,
Mr. MacKenzie.
Likewise.
Roger tells me that
perhaps we met on the level.
And we parted on the square.
[chuckles]
You are a Freemason?
Yes, although it's been years
since I've had a lodge.
For us as well,
but we mean to change that.
I'm organizing a meeting
to be held on the Ridge
every fortnight.
Be honored if you'd join us.
I'd be more than
pleased to attend.
Good.
Do you have another axe?
I'll lend a hand.
? ?
[Jones] We are gathered
together in the sight of God
to join this man and this woman
in holy matrimony.
And while the law
of the Commonwealth
of Pennsylvania means
to impede such a union,
the unjust laws of men
are no match
for the omnipotence of God.
-Amen.
-[all] Amen.
[glasses clinking]
[indistinct chatter]
[glass clinking]
As I look at the faces
in this room,
I am grateful for each of you
who came to bear witness
to our union.
Your steadfastness
gives me hope,
hope that those
who are absent today
will, in time,
open their hearts to us,
and hope that,
through hard work,
we will see Mr. Bryan's bill
pass the Assembly
and end the ban on marriages
such as ours.
Hear, hear.
[all] Hear, hear.
As the only member of
the Grey family in attendance,
I want to apologize to you,
Mercy.
We are a stubborn lot.
We have ideas about what
is right and what is wrong.
And we stand by them,
come what may.
Henry is no different.
He fell in love with you.
He knew that to be right,
and he stubbornly
would brook no opposition,
titles and expectations
be damned.
For that, I could not be
more proud of him.
[soft music plays]
Henry, I wish you
every happiness.
? ?
To the bride and groom.
[all] To the bride and groom.
[laughter and chatter]
? ?
If you'll excuse me. Thank you.
Thank you, cousin.
That was a wonderful speech.
Come with me a moment.
What's wrong?
Whatever do you mean?
Something's troubling you.
It's nothing.
I know when you're keeping
something from me.
We can talk tomorrow.
Today is for celebration-
Not until you tell me
what's bothering you.
It's your brother.
Ben?
What of him?
He was taken prisoner
by the Continentals.
Was leading a raiding party
in New Jersey.
Forgive me, Henry, I-
I did not want
to tell you this today...
...but he died
in their custody.
[somber music plays]
What?
How- how could this happen?
I don't know.
Apparently, Papa was given
very few details.
But he has a wife and son.
For their sake, I will
go and see what else I can
discover as to what happened.
What can you do?
You- you're no longer
in the army.
You resigned your commission.
I will do all I can.
Yes. Yes, of course.
You, um-
you must go.
? ?
I truly am sorry, Henry.
[crying]
[birds chirping]
[children laughing]
Have to say,
I don't think I'd ever met
a Quaker before
Ian brought you to the Ridge.
And is- is Quaker
the right word?
We say friend.
I'm certain you must have met
at least one.
You might not have known it
if the Quaker chose
not to speak in plain speech
when talking with thee.
Most of us don't have
stripes, spots,
or any other physical mark
by which they might discern us.
You know, I always wondered
what sort of woman
Ian would marry.
[sighs]
I couldn't have imagined
marrying a man named
Wolf's Brother either.
But there he is in my bed
every morning, nevertheless.
They do say the Lord moves
in mysterious ways.
-[laughs]
-That, He does.
I came to the Ridge
a widow with two bairns.
Never once did
I think a good man
like Evan Lindsay
would look at me,
much less ask to marry me.
[sighs]
To be filled
with such joy again-
Oh, these ants!
I'll move up a wee bit.
These wicked wee bletherskates
cannae be in all of them.
[grunting]
Whoop. Oh.
Are you all right?
I'm quite well.
[sighs]
He's just stretching,
pushing his little feet
into my ribs.
Though I'm afraid
he's running out of space.
[laughs]
In my final days with Rodney,
I felt like I was gonna burst.
Then, one morning,
he just popped out.
[chuckles]
Well, I thought
I had to visit the privy,
but I couldn't even reach
the chamber pot,
so I just squatted there
by the table.
And there he was.
-[laughter]
-Oh, Lizzie.
Well, don't get
your hopes up, Rachel.
That is not a very universal
birthing experience,
I'm afraid.
-[chuckles]
-Yes.
[sighs]
[ominous music plays]
[bear panting]
[dramatic music plays]
-Ah!
-Amy!
-[screaming]
[gunshot]
? ?
Claire!
-It's Amy!
-[Claire] What's happened?
-[Aidan] Ma!
-A bear.
[Brianna] Aidan! Aidan, Aidan.
[Aidan] Let me go!
Let me see her!
-Stay here.
-Let me go!
Aidan.
Just Mrs. Fraser do her work.
-Ma!
-Keep him in the kitchen.
Fanny, I need you
to step outside.
-[Amy gasping]
-[Aidan] Ma!
Roger's gone to fetch Evan.
Can you do something
at least until they arrive?
I haven't any laudanum.
Go get more bandages.
Aye.
[Amy moaning, rasping]
Amy, you're here with us.
Apply pressure there.
[Amy whimpering]
I want to go.
I want to see my ma.
You need to let Mrs. Fraser
help your mother right now.
Please.
[rasping]
[coughing]
[wheezing]
Aidan is here.
Evan's on his way with Orrie.
-[whimpering]
-I think I can hear them.
They're almost here.
All right?
-[Amy coughing]
-Look, they're here.
I'll see what's happenin'.
-Da.
-Come here to me. Adie.
-[Aidan] I want to see her.
-Claire, Evan's here.
[Evan] Here, here, here.
Aidan, Orrie.
She's lost a lot of blood,
and I think
she's bleeding internally.
There's nothing I can do.
[Evan] Don't be scared.
You're all right.
[somber music plays]
? ?
Adie, you listen.
Your ma will be all right.
She'll be all right.
? ?
I want to see her.
Aye. Go now.
Wait.
? ?
It's all right.
They should come.
Aye. Come.
Come, come.
You're all right.
? ?
[Claire] Amy, your husband
and sons are here.
Oh, dear God!
Amy.
? ?
Ma?
Please, wake up.
[crying]
Help her.
Mrs. Fraser, you help everyone.
Can you no' do something?
I'm so sorry, Evan.
Please.
I wish I could.
I'm so sorry.
[crying]
? ?
All is well.
You're safe now.
I'll take care of the boys.
I love you so much.
[Aidan] I love you, Ma.
Pray for her.
Pray- pray now.
Pray now before she goes.
? ?
God, be merciful unto us.
Hold her in the palm
of Thy hand.
Keep her always in the hearts
of her children,
for the Lord says, come to me,
all who labor
and are heavy laden,
and I will give you rest.
[sobbing]
[Young Ian]
Rachel, are you hurt?
What happened?
Are you well?
Is it wee Oggy?
No, he's well.
I'm well.
It's poor Amy.
A bear attacked her
in the woods.
Came out of nowhere.
One moment, she was there,
talking and laughing with us,
and then the next...
...she was on the ground.
It could have been
any one of us.
She's with the Lord now.
[crying]
God rest her soul.
[sobbing]
[dramatic music plays]
Halt there.
? ?
Captain.
There.
[William]
Thank you.
I'm afraid I don't have
much information
to share about the prisoner.
There was an outbreak
of jail fever.
He was one of the many
poor souls who succumbed to it.
I- I don't know what his family
was expecting to hear
beyond his circumstance.
Captain Lord Grey had
a wife and young son.
[sighs]
I only wish one day,
when he is old enough,
to tell him what I can about
what happened to his father.
That is all I'm asking for.
I'm sure you understand
that the details we received
were scant, to say the least.
Well, I am sorry.
Do send them
my sincerest condolences.
Did he leave anything
behind, perhaps?
Anything I could return to them
as a token of remembrance?
I'll make enquiries
with the surgeon,
find out if any of
the prisoner's belongings
have been stored.
I am sincerely obliged.
While I wait,
could one of your men
show me where
I might find his grave?
I had my rifle on me.
It all happened so fast, and-
I know, darling.
Are you all right?
Yeah. Mm.
Yeah. I will be.
Roger's with the kids.
I'm gonna go get ready
for the hunt.
I need to do something.
? ?
[Mrs. Cunningham]
Mrs. Fraser!
Mrs. Cunningham.
I've come to help.
I was at the trading post
when I heard what was ado.
Mr. Lindsay told me where
to find his wife's shroud.
Well, that's very
thoughtful of you.
But she already had one made?
Do you not, Mrs. Fraser?
No.
Perhaps I should.
Do you?
Well, of course.
At my age, I often think
I should sleep in it.
If you hold her steady,
I'll roll it down.
Well, I think
I should clean her first.
Oh, well, in that case,
you'll need more hot water.
I'll fetch a bucket.
In the kitchen.
Sure you want to be
part of this, Evan?
Aye, I do,
if it's the last thing I do.
And the lad?
Aye.
You're coming, too.
I am?
Aye, lad.
I'll help you track it.
But the kill is yours
and Mr. Lindsay's.
You hunted a bear before?
Dinna kill a bear
the way you kill a buck.
You want to aim for
the shoulder, just behind it.
That'll slow it enough
to take the final shot,
one to the heart.
That beast took your mother.
But you'll take its hide,
meat, and bones,
and you'll see to it, it will
never harm anyone ever again.
You ready?
I am.
Good.
Are you sure about this?
He's just a boy.
Aye.
He has a right to see
his mother avenged.
? ?
[horse nickers]
Salt to wash away sin
and to stop her ghost
from walking.
[soft music plays]
? ?
I was thinking that
we could keep the head covered
with a clean cloth
for the wake.
Could you not do a bit
to tidy her up?
Well...
...I could stitch together
part of the scalp
and use some of her hair
to cover the ear,
but there's not much I can do
about the eye, I'm afraid.
I've buried three husbands
and four children myself.
You always want to have
one last look upon the face,
no matter what's happened.
I'm so sorry.
I didn't know.
Well, how could you?
We've only just recently met.
? ?
Mrs. Cunningham, may I call you
by your Christian name?
Why, yes.
It's Elspeth.
And I'm Claire.
? ?
[dramatic music plays]
[gunshot]
? ?
-[gunshot]
-[horse neighs]
[suspenseful music plays]
? ?
[grunting]
[Jamie] Captain.
Mr. Fraser!
[panting]
Mr. Lindsay, your wife...
I'm so sorry
for you and your boys.
Your mother's been avenged.
This beast won't harm
anyone else.
I didn't want to waste time.
As I had a rifle with me,
I stayed out here
and followed the tracks.
But you could have died.
Oh, there was
no danger of that,
I assure you,
though this bear proved
a formidable foe.
I had to reload a time or two-
on the run, you might say.
Thank you, Captain.
[melancholy music plays]
? ?
[sighs] Ben.
I can't believe
it's come to this.
Goddamn this war.
? ?
[sniffles]
Amaranthus and Trevor are well.
Henry's married
the love of his life.
They're very happy.
I miss you.
And I've always considered you
to be my brother.
Be assured of this-
your son will learn
of his father's bravery.
Amy Lindsay is gone.
You knew her.
Her dooryard is
full of hollyhocks.
She came here with nothing.
She dared to hope
for a new life.
She made many friends.
She watched her two boys
grow strong.
She found love and joy again.
And she will be missed.
But her flowers still grow.
[gentle music plays]
? ?
[bees buzzing]
[birds calling]
The cabbage will eventually
make its own brine.
And once we're finished here,
we'll seal these
really tightly,
so the air can't get to it.
I'm going to need more salt.
I'll fetch it.
Can ye add something
to make it stink less?
Well, that's not
actually the sauerkraut.
That is the cabbage stew.
[Brianna] The sauerkraut
won't stink until later,
and there's nothing
you can do about it.
Oh, come now.
It's an excellent source
of nutrients and iron
and a wonderful cure
for heartburn,
especially
when you're pregnant.
And why in heaven
have we not made
this miracle remedy earlier?
Because I can't
control the seasons-
yet.
[chuckles]
Are you well?
[groans]
Mo chridhe?
Oh, it's happening.
Well, I don't think
there's any need
for the sauerkraut now.
Brianna, help me take her
into the surgery.
-[heavy breathing]
-Come on.
-[groans]
-You're all right.
? ?
[Young Ian] Auntie.
I've got her.
[Briana]
I've got you.
What's this for?
If-
when the bairn is born,
will you wrap him or her
in this?
No.
When your son
or daughter is born,
then you will wrap them
in this pelt yourself.
[Pvt. Thomas]
You the gentleman asking for
the British captain's
belongings?
Yes.
Are you the camp surgeon?
No, sir.
[chuckles]
But I, uh, make myself of use
where and when I can.
We've gathered what we had of
Captain Lord Grey's belongings.
Can I speak with the surgeon?
Afraid he's not here just now.
But I knew the captain.
Perhaps I can be of assistance.
You knew Captain Lord Grey?
Did you attend to him
when he lay dying?
No, sir.
But I remember him.
I did wish to ask more
questions about his last days.
Yes, I was, uh-
was sorry to hear he died.
He was a fine civil fellow,
the little that
I spoke with him,
and his condition
had much improved.
Had, sir?
Well, you'd hardly know
he was suffering.
But he passed overnight,
so they told me.
And by the next morning,
he'd already been buried.
I suppose the fever
can take you in the end,
even if you believe
you've conquered it.
[horse neighs]
[soft music plays]
? ?
[baby crying]
Mm-hmm.
[gasps]
Hello.
[baby cooing]
He's the most beautiful lad
I've ever seen.
Oh.
Have ye ever seen anything
as perfect as that, Auntie?
Never.
[baby crying]
Oh, he has a fierce grip,
this one.
? ?
[baby fussing]
Fanny.
What is it?
I thought you said
you'd seen a birth before.
At the brothel, no one was
ever happy about a baby coming.
[sighs]
Well, this is different.
Go on.
Do you know what
you'll call him yet?
Well, he's been Oggy
to us until now.
I'm told "og" means "young"
in the Gaelic.
Mandy was "Otto"
until she was Mandy.
I suppose now that he's here,
we should give him
a proper name.
I've been thinking,
what about Marmaduke?
Marmaduke Stevenson was
one of the Boston martyrs.
Was he not?
A very important friend.
And he wouldna be easily
mistaken for someone else.
What about Fox?
After George Fox, the founder
of the Society of Friends?
I dinna think highly
of foxes-
cunning wee creatures.
How about Wolf?
Next thing, we'll be wanting
to call him Rollo.
[chuckles]
That's not a bad idea.
He was a good dog.
[laughs]
[baby fussing]
Sorry I wasnae here.
Look at you,
beaming like the sun.
[chuckles]
I've never felt
anything like it before.
[chuckles]
Your wife and son
are sleeping sound.
[chuckles]
Oggy, is it?
For now.
Ye'll need to work on that.
[chuckles]
When Claire put the lad
in my arms,
it felt as though
everything changed.
Even the- the colors in the room
seemed different.
I never got to have that
with Swiftest of Lizards.
I- I- I was so filled
with love, and...
[soft music plays]
...only wish my da could have
been here to see wee Oggy.
He would have been very proud.
Maybe my ma can meet him
one day.
[chuckles]
Jenny will be over the moon.
[laughter]
? ?
You've been like a second
father to me my whole life,
Uncle Jamie.
I'll be comin' to ask
for yer advice.
I'm afraid I canna offer
anything in the way of advice.
I never got to do the things
you're about to do.
By the time I met Bree,
she was grown.
I didna ken Fergus as a babe,
and...
William...
...had to leave him
while he was still a young lad.
Ye'll get the chance
I never had.
I envy ye, lad.
Ye'll get to see
your son grow up.
Ye'll get to raise him
and teach him.
Ye'll ken what to do.
Ye will be everything
that the bairn needs.
Sl inte mhath 'ille,
agus beatha fhada shona.
Sl inte.
[chuckling]
[birds chittering]
[thunder rumbling]
? ?
Can I help you, sir?
That James Fraser's house?
'Tis.
Do you have business here?
My business is my own.
I'm Mrs. Fraser.
And his business is mine.
[laughing]
You'll find my husband
in the woodshed.
And you are?
[thunder rumbling]
Benjamin Cleveland.
Your servant,
General Fraser.
Not general, not anymore.
I resigned my commission.
Ken your name, sir.
I know yours, as well.
Yeah, I- I heard that
you resigned your commission
in order to tend
to your ailing wife.
She seems to have
recovered nicely.
You've got something to say,
sir, you say it.
Well, I just wanted to see
whether you were planning
to rejoin the army.
I'm not.
Why?
'Cause if not, I thought you
might be interested to know
that many of your countrymen
over the mountains,
landowners like myself,
are raising our own militia
in order to protect
their families
and their property.
Who might these men be?
Uh, John Sevier, Isaac Shelby,
William Campbell-
a good many others,
I can tell you.
Who are they protecting
their land from?
Tories, mostly.
Indians, as well.
I saw some bodies
hanging in a tree recently
near the treaty line.
You wouldn't happen to know
anything about that?
Mm.
Mm, yeah.
I would.
I done it- retaliation.
For what?
Those men were Tories, sir.
I thought I already said that.
Their beliefs
their only offense?
I hate a Tory.
Loyalist pigs.
Hung a few of them now.
I don't keep count.
Puts a scare into the others.
[laughs]
? ?
There's a Tory
on your land, I hear.
A man named Cunningham.
I'm aware of
Captain Cunningham.
Captain, is it?
[laughs]
Oh, you see there?
There's just no telling where
the British might crop up.
So you come join me in my band,
and I- I can help you
with that.
Over a hundred strong now,
more joining every day.
Mr. Cleveland,
I turned down
George Washington himself.
What makes you think I would
change my mind for you?
It's just
a friendly invitation,
one neighbor to another.
I'll handle the captain,
and anything that needs
my attention
on my land.
Good day, Mr. Cleveland.
Yeah.
Good day.
[thunder rumbles]
Cleveland.
Wasn't that one of the names
Frank mentioned?
Aye.
That was him.
Says he kens the others, too,
wants me to fight with them.
So then you are
the James Fraser in the book.
[dramatic music plays]
? ?
He says I
ought to kill Cunningham.
What's his reasoning?
Says the man's a danger to me.
Aye, but is there
any truth in it?
Does Frank's book mention him?
No.
Cunningham's retired.
Well, so he says.
Well, we have Lodge.
You planned to keep
an eye on him.
Maybe he let something slip.
Aye.
Am I in the book?
In the battle?
No.
Not sure if I should be
relieved or offended.
Frank doesn't mention
any of my men in the battle,
not one name.
Can't imagine fighting
wi'out them.
Because maybe you don't.
Well, we'll start with Lodge,
see what we find out.
I'll, uh-
I'll go back to the work.
Thanks.
[door clicks]
Does Roger know?
About the battle?
Aye.
Didna tell him
that Frank says I die.
Good.
Because you won't.
Glad you think so.
I know so.
[pensive music plays]
Twenty years,
he and I lived together.
And he never once mentioned it.
? ?
He made me promise
not to look for you.
That was his condition
for taking me back
and raising Brianna.
All the while,
he was searching for you,
found you,
kept it from me.
Why?
If he cared
half as much for you as I do,
he'd do whatever he could
to keep you wi' him.
But how could obsessively
searching for you in history
keep me with him?
Maybe he wasn't
searching for me, Claire.
Maybe he was searching for you,
to see if you'd leave him.
[indistinct chatter]
You know the rules, Gordon.
There's no weapons in Lodge.
I'll leave it out here then.
Go leave it in your home
and come back.
[indistinct chatter]
Worshipful master.
Let us invoke the assistance
of the Great Architect
of the Universe
in all our undertakings.
May our labors,
thus begun in order,
be conducted in peace
and closed in harmony.
[all] So mote it be.
I declare this Lodge
duly open
for the purposes
of Freemasonry.
When we gather in this place,
we set aside our politics
and our religious differences.
If you have quarrels,
let them be settled here.
If you have concerns
or find yourselves in need,
may you bring this
to your brothers
that we may lift you up.
My hope for this meeting
is to strengthen the ties
that bind us together,
in service to
the greater good of all.
Is there any man
who would like to start?
I would, if I may.
Brother Cunningham.
Is it true that the captain
hunted that bear
all by himself?
Aye, that he did.
As many of you know,
we recently buried a kind soul,
a fine member of our community.
I'm sure I speak
for every man here
when I say you have our
sympathies and our support.
You have looked into the face
of one you have loved
and seen death.
I have done the same.
First, when I lost my wife,
when she gave birth
to my son, Simon.
Then again, two years ago.
I was a captain in
Burgoyne's army at Saratoga.
Simon had joined the army
as first lieutenant.
He was only eighteen,
but he fought valiantly.
I was no more than
a few feet away from him
when the shot struck him,
and I caught him in my arms.
[somber music plays]
I felt him die.
? ?
He was laid
in the hospital tent,
and I sat down beside him.
I cannot say
what I thought or what I felt.
The space within me was void.
? ?
But while I sat,
I watched his face,
and I saw the light
enter it again.
And then he opened his eyes,
and he spoke to me.
He said,
"Don't worry, Father.
I'll see you again
in seven years."
And then
he closed his eyes and...
was dead once more.
I realized
the Lord had given me a sign,
the sure knowledge
that the soul
is not destroyed by death.
And I had been given reprieve.
In seven years,
I would see my son again,
but not before.
I would not taste death
until that day.
So I have come among you
in answer to God's call.
I am here because
I wish to use my time wisely.
Honor those that you have lost
as I intend to honor
the memory of my son,
First Lieutenant
Simon Elmore Cunningham.
Cherish your sons,
your daughters, your wives,
while you yet have them.
[all] So mote it be.
[Roger]
Rousing speech.
That's one word for it.
Incredible might be another.
You doubt he heard
a call from God?
Oh, that's not
the part I doubt,
although I do wonder
what he thinks
he was called here to do.
A man being called by God
is one thing.
A man who thinks he canna die,
is quite another.
[pensive music plays]
[owl hoots]
? ?
[dramatic music plays]
[grunts]
[gasping]
Thank Christ.
[panting]
[laughs]
[Frank] Seven years from
Saratoga, Cunningham said,
so he has five more years
to live.
He's not the only one
who knows
the day of his death.
[pensive music plays]
? ?
Sassenach.
Sorry.
Jamie.
I need you.
-Mm.
-I need you.
? ?
[moaning]
[both moaning]
[sighing]
[grunts]
[moaning]
[grunting]
? ?
[panting]
[Frank] You're going to die.
[foreboding music plays]
? ?
Who will hold her
once you're gone?
? ?